Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad

Summary

I am a PhD candidate focusing on Reinforcement Learning. I have 9+ years of fundamental research and industry experience in developing advanced Machine Learning, Deep Learning and Reinforcement Learning solutions to real-world problems, focusing on human-centred AI, virtual reality, human-computer interaction, and cognitive science. My expertise and interests include but are not limited to Reinforcement Learning, generative models, and large language models. I am a skilled communicator with a track record of publishing research and delivering compelling presentations.

Education

Doctor of Philosophy, Computing Science

Sept 2018 – Dec 2024 [expected]

University of Alberta, Edmonton, Canada

Related Coursework:

- o Intro to Virtual/Augmented Reality and Telepresence o Machine Learning and the Brain
- o Image Processing and Analysis in Diagnostic Imaging

Master of Science, Computer Engineering/Artificial Intelligence

Sept 2014 – Aug 2017

Shahid Beheshti University, Tehran, Iran

Related Coursework:

- Machine Learning
 Neural Network
 Image Processing
- Pattern Recognition
 Data Mining
 Natural Language Processing

Bachelor of Science, Computer Engineering/Software Engineering

Sept 2009 – Aug 2014

University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

Related Coursework:

- Advanced ProgrammingData Structures
- Database DesignArtificial Intelligence
- Intro to MultimediaIntro to eLearning

- Operating Systems
- Human-Computer Interaction

Qualifications

- Python
- Microsoft.NET
- Jupyter
- Unity

- Pytorch
- SQL
- Google Colab
- Java

- MATLAB
- OpenAl Gym
- MS Visual Studio
 Git

Related Experience

Intern Research Scientist, Samsung Research Montreal

Jun 2022-Apr 2023

- o Implemented and evaluated reinforcement learning architectures to optimize agent performance.
- Developed curriculum learning techniques to effectively train RL agents.
- Implemented a Vector Quantized Variational Autoencoder for efficient high-dimensional data clustering.
- Adapted and integrated an existing Online Decision Transformer within our RL framework.

PhD research Experience

Sept 2018-Now

- Designed and developed adaptive virtual reality exposure therapy environments leveraging machine learning methods to estimate stress levels based on physiological measures and reinforcement learning algorithms to personalize the VR experience.
- \circ Conducted human subject studies (n=30+) to evaluate the effectiveness of the developed VR system.

Research Engineer, Pars Cognition

Sept 2017-Aug 2018

Developed mini-serious video games within the field of cognitive science.

Master research Experience

Sept 2014-Sept 2017

- Designed and developed a serious video game to investigate differences in in-game behaviour between normal and autistic children. Conducted a human subject study involving collecting data on game interactions.
- Applied machine learning techniques to analyze game data and identify key behavioural patterns differentiating normal and autistic children.

Selected Projects

Virtual Reality/Games

- Develop different Virtual Reality environments that induce fear in the subjects Unity
- Develop a Virtual Reality environment with adaptive parameters Unity
- Develop small serious video games GameMaker and Unity

Machine Learning/Deep Learning/Reinforcement Learning

- Develop an adaptive system using Experience-driven Procedural Content Generation via Reinforcement Learning -Python, , OpenAl Gym
- o Develop Online Decision Transformer Python, Pytorch
- Develop Vector Quantized Variational Autoencoder for time-series clustering Python, Pytorch
- Heart rate estimation from video via CNN Python, PyTorch
- o Develop curriculum learning for reinforcement learning- Python, OpenAl Gym
- Estimate stress level Based on physiological response via traditional machine learning methods and LSTM -Python, Scikit learn, Pytorch
- Apply machine learning to find different patterns of behavior in the game Matlab
- o Implementation of using Neural Network for detecting impulse noise Matlab
- Implementation of a hidden semi-Markov model with missing data and multiple observation sequences for mobility tracking - Java

Publications

- Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad, Matthew Guzdial, and Pierre Boulanger. "Spiders Based on Anxiety: How Reinforcement Learning Can Deliver Desired User Experience in Virtual Reality Personalized Arachnophobia Treatment" [under review 2024].
- Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad, Matthew Guzdial, and Pierre Boulanger. "Arachnophobia Exposure Therapy using Experience-driven Procedural Content Generation via Reinforcement Learning (EDPCGRL)." Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment. Vol. 17. No. 1. 2021.
- Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad. "Automated Personalized Exposure Therapy Based on Physiological Measures
 Using Experience-Driven Procedural Content Generation." Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on
 Artificial Intelligence and Interactive Digital Entertainment. Vol. 17. No. 1. 2021.
- Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad, Pierre Boulanger, and Matthew Guzdial. "Adaptive Virtual Reality Exposure Therapy Based on Physiological Measures." 25th Anniversary Annual International CyberPsychology, CyberTherapy & Social Networking Conference (CYPSY25). 2021.
- Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad, Hadi Moradi, and Hamid-Reza Pouretemad. "The Differences Between Children with Autism and Typically Developed Children in Using a Hand-Eye-Coordination Video Game." International Conference on Ubiquitous Computing and Ambient Intelligence. Springer, 256-264. 2017.
- Shadan Golestan, Athar Mahmoudi-Nejad, and Hadi Moradi. "A framework for easier designs: Augmented intelligence in serious games for cognitive development." IEEE Consumer Electronics Magazine 8.1, 19-24. 2018.

Achievements

Olympiad Competition Award

2008

Awarded in the Math and Literature Olympiads for pre-university students

Ranked 459th the Undergraduate Nationwide Universities Entrance Exam

2009

Undergraduate Nationwide Universities Entrance Exam in Iran with more than 300,000 participants

Ranked 65th the Graduate Nationwide Universities Entrance Exam

2014

o Graduate Nationwide Universities Entrance Exam in Iran with more than 30,000 participants

Additional Experience

Teaching Assistant Experience

Sept 2018-Now

- Courses: File and Database Management, Artificial Intelligence in Games, Virtual/Augmented Reality and Telepresence, Introduction to Human Computer Interaction, Introduction to GPU Programming.
- · Lecturing in lab sessions, design and grading assignments and exams, holding office hours, and proctoring exams.

Treasurer Role at CSGSA

Sept 2019-Sept 2020

Computer Science Graduate Student Association (CSGSA) is a voluntary group at the University of Alberta which
offers support and activities for Computing Science graduate students